Soviet Union Registered Baptists Subject Files, Inclusive: 1890-2006, undated, Bulk: 1961-1998
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union Registered Baptists Subject Files
Inclusive: 1890-2006, undated, Bulk: 1961-1998
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
22
Keston Institute, 1969 -
6 A4 Document Boxes
The Soviet Union Registered Baptist Subject Files contain a variety of materials on the history and persecution of the Registered Baptist Church and the life and hardship of its clergy and members in the former Soviet Union.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
From the beginning of the post-World War II period until approximately 2007, Keston obtained materials documenting the religious and political climate and persecution of Registered Baptists in the Soviet Union, a minority group which suffered under communism from 1947 to 1989.
The Soviet Baptist movement began about 1867 when the first Slavic Baptist, Nikita Voronin, was baptized in Georgia Although the Soviet Baptist Church has been a minority, it has had a powerful global impact. Though the Church has experienced brief periods of relative religious freedom during both the Lenin and Gorbachev eras, believers overall have experienced intense persecution in the officially atheist nation. Examples of Baptist persecution includes emigration complications, church repossession, job insecurity, house searches, imprisonment, and murder.
Legally, the Baptist Church had religious freedom although the reality was complex. They had the right to assemble and an official national administrative organization, the All-Union Council of Evangelical Christian Baptists (AUCECB) with meetings every four years. However, they were denied the ability to have Sunday schools, bring their children to church, public evangelism, or owning a Bible in many cases. The rights were available to Baptist churches only if they registered with the state and complied with regulations. The reality varied by region and time period. Additionally, legislation was often slanted. For example, citizens could legally exercise the right to create atheistic propaganda but not religious advertising.
Naturally, these created tensions. In 1961, tensions in the church climaxed, leading notable Baptist leader Georgi Vins to form a different type of Baptist church. He believed that the Baptist Church was too involved and compliant with the Soviet authorities and thus chose not to register his new Baptist church as a way to separate from both the national Baptist Church and the Soviet authorities. Thus, the Registered Baptist Church and the Unregistered Baptist Church known as “Initsiativniki” became two denominations. While reconciliation is a high priority for the AUCECB in the post-Soviet era and some unregistered churches have rejoined, the two Baptist groups are still divided.
Important Representative Events
The Registered Baptist General Files document the Church’s experience in the Soviet Union throughout the 20th century. This section details summaries of five carefully chosen events that best demonstrate the defining characteristics of the Soviet Baptist movement. These include the emigration case of Valeri Barinov, the murder and cover-up of soldier Viktor Sedletsky, the handling of visits from foreign officials, the controversy around AUCECB leaders such as Alexei Bychkov, and the reality of theological education for Baptists.
Valeri Barinov was a 43-year-old rock musician and a fervent believer when he was sentenced to one of the worst labor camps in the Soviet Union. His crime was the secret production of “The Trumpet Call” which was a rock opera of the Gospel. Barinov spent years in almost complete isolation with no mail or family visits. Despite the circumstances, his spirit remained unbroken, and he experienced great spiritual success in converting other prisoners. Barinov spent years trying to secure emigration for himself and his family to England before international pressure finally convinced the Soviet government to allow his emigration in the mid-1980’s. Despite persecution, Barinov remained a vivacious force for God in the West and later returned as a missionary to the Soviet Union in the 1990’s. His case represents the strength and perseverance of the Baptist movement in the face of hardship and how with the help of foreign allies, Baptists were often able to secure some level of resolution to their governmental issues.
Another case, that of Viktor Sedletsky, ended differently, perhaps because of the lack of international pressure. He was a young believer in his twenties when drafted into Soviet army. After months of coercion to renounce his faith, his commanders resorted to torture. Sedletsky remained steadfast, and as a result, tortured to death. His body was returned to his village in a coffin nailed shut with a KGB escort and an official story claiming he died in an accident during a military exercise. The village was outraged and demanded to see his body. Locals held the officers back as they pried open the coffin which revealed obvious torture wounds, including extensive bruising, missing fingernails, and rags in place of eyes. Officially, Viktor Sedletsky’s case file states that he died in an accident during training.
The cases of Barinov and Sedletsky demonstrate how important foreign awareness was in securing justice for the persecuted. This naturally leads to the question of the condition of visits from the West. Official visits were relatively frequent, including those by Baptist World Alliance (BWA) officials, evangelist Billy Graham, and President Richard Nixon. However, Soviet authorities carefully managed each trip. Delegations were shuttled to the Moscow Baptist Church, the only one in all of the city, for a rousing demonstration of religious freedom in the assembly of over 2,000 Baptists during a Sunday service. However, delegations were not given the opportunity to see other churches, and when religious protests occurred, they were concealed. The biased lens typical is summarized in the words of a believer during a protest against the 1970 visit of BWA President William Tolbert of Liberia, “Your visit was to the AUCECB -- a state shop window for religious freedomEL From the heights of a royal visit, it is of course difficult to notice the tears of the orphans and widows.” In this way, the reality of the Iron Curtain was visible even as foreign officials visited to ensure Baptists were granted religious freedoms.
How did the Soviet government so effectively deceive during visits from foreign officials? The key was having men on the inside. Through the decades, there has been controversy around several AUCECB officials such as Michael Zhidkov, Ilia Orlov, Sergei Nikolaev, and most notably, Alexei Bychkov. All were accused of being KGB agents tasked with infiltrating the AUCECB as a way to control Baptist activity. Bychkov’s case is most notable as he was the General Secretary for the organization. He was also given a medal for religious activity and authority by the state. It is also worth noting that AUCECB delegations that visited abroad always consisted of men accused of being KGB agents. He claimed on many occasions that the Baptist Church was not persecuted, that only churches who didn’t comply with the state experienced difficulties. In this way, the Soviet government indirectly managed Baptist activity.
Theological education also demonstrates difficulties Baptists faced. Often, they were not allowed to have official theological classes, only correspondence lessons through Moscow. For decades, Baptists fought for a theological seminary in Moscow which was finally built in the 1980’s. For some, international education was an option, and several ministers studied at seminaries in Germany or England. However, given the expense, the pastor of an individual church was often determined by a community vote on who had the greatest religious expertise. Some were as young as seventeen. Young adults stepped up not because they knew everything they needed, but simply because they were needed.
The Registered Baptist Church in the Soviet Union was a minority with perseverance and spiritual vibrance that served as an inextinguishable light. Despite the state’s carefully curated image of religious freedom for foreign dignitaries and infiltration, Baptists continued to smuggle the truth to the West so that others, including the Keston Institute, could tell their story. Although they lacked theological education, they relied on God to guide them. The Registered Baptist Church thus was and continues to be an inspiration for believers around the world.
Scope and Content
The Registered Baptist General Files consist of a variety of materials. The most common are leaflets, booklets, newspaper articles, clippings, newsletters, lists, handwritten notes, and cross references. However, some correspondence, publication references, magazines, book chapters, interview transcripts, legal documents, biographies, maps, pamphlets, theses, book covers, and email transcripts are also included along with some photos and visual propaganda. The bulk of information spans from the 1960’s to the 1990’s. These records were compiled and created to safely archive and verify stories of persecution within the Soviet Union.
Notable individuals found in the collection include Michael Bourdeaux, Georgi Vins, Alexander Karev, Nikita Voronin, Ilia Orlov, Valeri Barinov, Lidija Doronina-Lasmane, Viesturs Kalnins, Janis Smits, Janis Rozkalns, Logvinenko, V. Strelnikov, A. Semchenko, A. Butylin, Anatoly Stoyan, Alexei Stoyan, Sergei Nikolaev, P. K. Shatrov, Mikhail Zhidkov, Ilya Ivanov Viktor Sedletsky, Gerhard Claas, Richard Nixon, Andrew MacRae, Billy Graham, Revd Dr. David Russell, William Bright, Claus Meister, Daniels and Rudite Bruvers, Jakov Dukhonchenko, and Alf Dickson.
Important events and topics include the quadrennial AUCECB Congresses, legislation changes affecting churches, representation in secular press, repossession/demolition of Baptist churches, church registration, anti-religious propaganda and slander, persecution of believers (house searches, imprisonment, murder, forced psychiatric treatment, etc), mass baptisms, defection from the faith, church-organized charity, Western protests and aid to Baptists, visits from foreign delegations and visits from the USSR to the West, discussions on religion, theological education and training, and calls for peace talks and disarmament.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received most of the Registered Baptists materials in files organized by specific categories. This original filing system has been preserved. Items received by the Keston Center in no particular order are arranged thematically and chronologically.
The Registered Baptist Subject Files are arranged into two series: I. General and II. Samizdat.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 22.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Barinov, Valeri Alexandrovich, 1944-; Butylin, Alexander.; Bychkov, Aleksei.; Dickson, Alf.; Kalnins, Viesturs.; Lasmane-Doron¸ina, Lidija, 1925-; Rozkalns, Janis.; Semchenko, Alexander.; Smits, Janis.; Strelnikov, Viktor.
Subjects (Organizations)
Vsesoi︠u︡znyiămp;& sovet evangel)'skikh khristian-baptistov (Soviet Union).
Places
Soviet Union -- Church history.
Subjects
Baptism -- Baptists -- Soviet Union.; Baptist church buildings -- Soviet Union.; Baptists -- Clergy.; Baptists -- Soviet Union -- History.; Charity -- Religious aspects -- Christianity -- Soviet Union.; Church and state -- Soviet Union -- History.; Demonstrations -- Religious aspects -- Christianity.; Freedom of religion -- Soviet Union.; Human rights -- Soviet Union.; Legislation -- Soviet Union.; Persecution -- Soviet Union -- History.; Propaganda, Soviet.; Religion and state -- Soviet Union.; Religious education.; Underground Literature -- Soviet Union.
Genres
Cassette tape; Reel to reel tapes; Academic theses.; Booklets.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Correspondence.; Leaflets (printed works); Legal instruments.; Maps.; Newsletters.; Pamphlets.; Periodicals.; Photographs.; Records (Documents); Registers (Lists).; Transcripts.
- General, 1890-2006, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The Registered Baptist General Files document the history of the Registered Baptist Church in the Soviet Union, following both the issues they have faced as well as their growth in numbers and religious freedom. The documents are in good condition.
  - Registered Baptist Church History. General, 1931-1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Registered Baptist Church History. General, 1975-1994 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - History. General, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Registered Baptist Church History. General, undated (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
  - Registered Baptist Church History. Soviet Period, 1967-1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Registered Baptist Church History. Soviet Period, 1982-1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Individual Members of Registered Baptist Church. General, 1966-2005 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Individual Members of Registered Baptist Church. Barinov, Valeri, 1983-1988 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Individual Members of Registered Baptist Church. Doronina-Lasmane, Lidija, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Individual Members of Registered Baptist Church. Kalnins, Viesturs, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Individual Members of Registered Baptist Church. Smits, Janis, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Individual Members of Registered Baptist Church. Smits, Janis, 1976-1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Individual Members of Registered Baptist Church. Rozkalns, Janis, 1983-1987 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lists of Registered Baptist Churches, 1974-1992 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Individual Registered Baptist Churches. General, 1968-1991 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Individual Registered Baptist Churches. Moscow Oblast, 1970-1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Individual Registered Baptist Churches. Ukraine, 1945-1986 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Individual Registered Baptist Churches. Soviet territories minus Ukraine, 1970-1982 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Registered Baptist Church Administration. AUCECB, 1960-1991 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Registered Baptist Church Administration. AUCECB. General, 1944-1992 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Registered Baptist Church Administration. 39th, 40th, and 41st AUCECB Congresses, 1966-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Registered Baptist Church Administration. 42nd, 43rd, and 44th AUCECB Congresses, 1979-1990 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Registered Baptist Church-State Relations, 1966-1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Registered Baptist Church-State Relations, 1977-1989 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Registered Baptist Church. State Legislation, 1966-1990 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Registered Baptist Church. Council for Religious Affairs, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Registered Baptist Church. Opening of New, Reopening, Consecration, and Reconsecration of Church Buildings, 1976-1992 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Registered Baptist Church. State Registration, 1977-2002 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Registered Baptist Church. Commendation in Secular Press, 1966-2005 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - State's Oppressive Practices Toward Registered Baptist Church and Its Members., 1929-2005 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Harassment of Members of Registered Baptist Church, 1962-1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Physical Assault and Murder of Members of Registered Baptist Church, 1964-2006 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Registered Baptist Church. Disruption of Meetings and Denial of Right to Assemble, 1973-1990 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Registered Baptist Church. State Fines, 1978-1981 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Trials of Individual Members of Registered Baptist Church. General, 1937-2000 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Trials of Individual Members of Registered Baptist Church. Charges against V. Strelnikov, A. Semchenko, and A. Butylin, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Imprisonment of Individual Members of Registered Baptist Church., 1961-1995 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Expulsion of Individual Members of Registered Baptist Church., 1890-1979 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Legal disabilities of Registered Baptist Church. State's Refusal of Registration. Closure of Churches, 1977-1988 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - State Infiltration into Registered Baptist Church, 1965-1983 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - State Expropriation, Demolition, or Desecration of Registered Baptist Churches. General, 1976-1999 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - State Expropriation, Demolition, or Desecration of Registered Baptist Churches. State destruction of Baptist church in Bryansk, August 30, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Maltreatment of Registered Baptist Church Members in the Army, 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Maltreatment of Registered Baptist Church Members in the Army. Murder and Cover-Up of Soldier V. Sedletsky, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Discrimination of Registered Baptist Church Members in Employment, 1963-1988 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Misuse of Psychiatry Toward Registered Baptist Church Members, 1973-1982 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Attacks on Registered Baptist Church and Its Members in the Media and At Public Meetings (1 of 3), 1961-1969 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Attacks on Registered Baptist Church and Its Members in the Media and At Public Meetings (2 of 3), 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Attacks on Registered Baptist Church and Its Members in the Media and At Public Meetings (3 of 3), 1973-1995 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Registered Baptist Church Members' House Searches, Literature and Property Confiscation, 1977-1983 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Registered Baptist Church Members' Loss of Parental Rights, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Registered Baptist Church Life, 1950-1972 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Registered Baptist Church Life, 1974-1991 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Registered Baptist Church Festivals and Anniversaries, 1961-1975 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Registered Baptist Church Festivals and Anniversaries, 1976-1997 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Registered Baptist Church Services and Rituals, 1969-1985 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Registered Baptist Church Services and Rituals. Personal accounts of baptisms, 1964-1988 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Modernizations: Actions and Attitudes, 1975-1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Registered Baptist Church. Preaching, Evangelism, and Conversions, 1959-1977 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Registered Baptist Church. Preaching, Evangelism, and Conversions, 1978-1993 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Registered Baptist Church. Parish Life, 1956-1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Registered Baptist Church Members' Defection from the Faith, 1962-1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Registered Baptist Church Official Publications. General, 1970-1998 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Registered Baptist Church Official Publications. "Bratsky Vestnik." General, 1967-1975 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Registered Baptist Church's Official Publications. "Bratsky Vestnik." General, 1976-1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Registered Baptist Church's Official Publications. "Bratsky Vestnik." Biographical Index, 1947-1971 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Registered Baptist Church's Official Publications. "Bratsky Vestnik." Biographical Index, 1972-1977 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Registered Baptist Church's Official Publications. "Bratsky Vestnik." Biographical Index, 1978-1982 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Registered Baptist Church's Official Publications. "Bratsky Vestnik." Biographical Card Index, 1947-1957 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Registered Baptist Church's Official Publications. "Bratsky Vestnik." Content Sheets, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Registered Baptist Church's Official Publications. "Bratsky Vestnik." Geographical Index, 1946-1966 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Registered Baptist Church's Official Publications. "Bratsky Vestnik." Geographical Index, 1967-1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Registered Baptist Church's Official Publications. "Bratsky Vestnik." Geographical Index, 1977-1982 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Registered Baptist Church's Official Publications. "Bratsky Vestnik." Tables of Content, 1945-1977 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Registered Baptist Church's Revival, Charismatic Renewal, 1970-1991 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Registered Baptist Church Members Excommunication, 1974-1986 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Registered Baptist Church Philanthropic Activities, 1985-2000 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Registered Baptist Church Clergy and Priesthood, 1976-1985 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Registered Baptist Church Clergy Hierarchy, 1960-1990 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Registered Baptist Church Clergy. Ordination, Election, Retirement, Death, 1967-1976 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Registered Baptist Church Clergy. Ordination, Election, Retirement, Death, 1977-1990 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Individual Registered Baptist Clergy. General, 1964-1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Individual Registered Baptist Clergy. Bychkov, Aleksei, 1970-1988 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Working and Living Conditions of Registered Baptist Clergy, 1976-1981 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Registered Baptist Church Clergy and Priesthood. Statistics, 1943-1990 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Registered Baptist Church's International Relations, 1962-1991 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Western Reactions to Persecution of Registered Baptist Church. Protests, Appeals, Aid, 1964-1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Western Reactions to Persecution of Registered Baptist Church. Protests, Appeals, Aid, 1978-2000 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Registered Baptist Church's Contacts with International Organizations, 1974-1991 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Registered Baptist Church Delegations' Visits Abroad, 1969-1990 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Registered Baptist Church. Visits from Foreign Delegations, 1969-1976 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Registered Baptist Church. Visits from Foreign Delegations, 1977-1991 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Registered Baptist Church Activities Disapproved by the State. Meetings and Prayer Groups, 1976-1989 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Registered Baptist Church Activities Disapproved by the State. Public Demonstrations and Protests, 1973-1984 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Registered Baptist Church Activities Disapproved by the State. Defense of Believers' Rights and Litigation, 1971-1988 (Box 4, Folder 14)